primary keys, foreign key constraints, and default values. CREATE TABLE IF NOT EXISTS project_documents ( id UUID PRIMARY KEY DEFAULT uuid_generate_v4(), project_id UUID REFERENCES projects(id) ON DELETE CASCADE, title TEXT NOT NULL, content TEXT, doc_type TEXT NOT NULL DEFAULT 'other', file_url TEXT, created_by UUID REFERENCES auth.users(id), created_at TIMESTAMP WITH TIME ZONE DEFAULT NOW() ); 7.2 Appendix B: Sample Data Transformation Logic This JavaScript code snippet demonstrates a common pattern used in the frontend service layer. Its purpose is to map database snake_case field names to the camelCase convention to align with frontend development standards, ensuring consistency and ease of use for developers. // Mapping database snake_case to frontend camelCase
if (table === 'candidates' && key === 'job_id') newKey = 'jobId';
if (table === 'interviews' && key === 'date') newKey = 'scheduledAt';
TalentOps Backend System: Data Architecture & Design
Document Control
-------------------------------------------------------------------------------- 
1.0 Introduction and Architectural Philosophy
This document serves as the authoritative technical specification for the TalentOps backend data architecture. Its purpose is to provide a comprehensive blueprint for development, ensure architectural consistency across the platform, and serve as a foundational reference for technical reviews and future enhancements. This architecture is governed by a core philosophy that prioritizes stability, scalability, and readiness for future AI-driven capabilities. The TalentOps data design philosophy is built upon three core tenets:
Relational Integrity This principle is strictly enforced through the use of PostgreSQL foreign keys. By mandating relationships at the database level, we guarantee data consistency and reliability across the entire system. This approach prevents orphaned records and ensures that critical connections between entities, such as a user's assignment to a project, remain valid and trustworthy. Logical Multi-tenancy The architecture is designed for robust data isolation through a strategy of scoping data at both the organization and project levels. This hierarchical structure is a strategic decision that prepares the platform to support multiple distinct clients in the future. It ensures that data for one client is logically and securely separated from another, providing a scalable foundation for growth into an enterprise-grade SaaS offering. RAG-Ready Design The platform employs a hybrid storage model that combines the strengths of structured relational data in PostgreSQL with unstructured vector data in ChromaDB. This is a strategic decision to de-risk future AI development and establish a competitive advantage. By pre-integrating vector storage for Retrieval-Augmented Generation (RAG) workflows, the platform is positioned to power sophisticated AI-driven features like intelligent search and context-aware assistants with minimal future re-architecture. This philosophy is brought to life by a carefully selected technology stack, which is detailed in the following section.
strengths of structured relational data in PostgreSQL with unstructured vector data in ChromaDB. This is a strategic decision to de-risk future AI development and establish a competitive advantage. By pre-integrating vector storage for Retrieval-Augmented Generation (RAG) workflows, the platform is positioned to power sophisticated AI-driven features like intelligent search and context-aware assistants with minimal future re-architecture. This philosophy is brought to life by a carefully selected technology stack, which is detailed in the following section. 2.0 High-Level System Architecture
The decision to build TalentOps on a serverless architecture is a strategic one, aimed at maximizing scalability while minimizing operational overhead. This approach allows the development team to focus on feature delivery rather than infrastructure management, enabling faster iteration and providing the ability to handle fluctuating workloads seamlessly. The architecture is composed of two primary components. The core technology stack includes:
Backend-as-a-Service (BaaS): The system leverages Supabase, which provides a managed PostgreSQL database along with a suite of backend services. This serves as the primary repository for all structured, operational data. AI Gateway: A specialized service is dedicated to managing unstructured vector data. This gateway utilizes ChromaDB as its vector database to power semantic search and other AI-driven functionalities. The fundamental data hierarchy of the system is designed for clear separation of concerns and operational control: Organization > Project > User. Organization: This represents the highest-level container. It is implicit in the current single-instance deployment but is architected to support future multi-organizational scaling, directly enabling the logical multi-tenancy philosophy. Project: The primary operational unit. All core activities, including hiring, tasks, and document management, are scoped to a project. User: Individuals are assigned to one or more projects through a persistent mapping layer (project_members), granting them specific access and permissions within that project's context.
Project > User. Organization: This represents the highest-level container. It is implicit in the current single-instance deployment but is architected to support future multi-organizational scaling, directly enabling the logical multi-tenancy philosophy. Project: The primary operational unit. All core activities, including hiring, tasks, and document management, are scoped to a project. User: Individuals are assigned to one or more projects through a persistent mapping layer (project_members), granting them specific access and permissions within that project's context. This high-level architecture provides the framework for the detailed entity relationships and data models that follow. 3.0 Detailed Data Model & Entity Relationships
This section serves as the core of the technical specification, deconstructing the entity relationship model that underpins the TalentOps platform. It details the schema of the primary data entities and clarifies the logical connections between them, which dictate the system's business logic and operational capabilities. The key relationships between the system's entities are summarized as follows:
A Many-to-Many relationship exists between PROFILES and PROJECTS, facilitated by the PROJECT_MEMBERS junction table. This design is crucial for operational flexibility, allowing a single user, such as a consultant, to be an active member of multiple projects simultaneously. The recruitment module features a clear parent-child relationship, where each JOB requisition acts as a container for multiple CANDIDATES, each of whom may have multiple INTERVIEWS. Operational TASKS are contextually linked to both a PROJECT to define their scope and a PROFILE to assign ownership and responsibility. The AUDIT_LOG entity serves as a comprehensive, system-wide ledger, capturing all data modifications to ensure full traceability and support compliance requirements. The logical representation of these entity relationships is illustrated in the diagram below.

 3.1 Core Entity Definitions
The following subsections define the schema for the primary entities in the TalentOps data model.
INTERVIEWS. Operational TASKS are contextually linked to both a PROJECT to define their scope and a PROFILE to assign ownership and responsibility. The AUDIT_LOG entity serves as a comprehensive, system-wide ledger, capturing all data modifications to ensure full traceability and support compliance requirements. The logical representation of these entity relationships is illustrated in the diagram below. 3.1 Core Entity Definitions The following subsections define the schema for the primary entities in the TalentOps data model. 3.1.1 Profiles (Users)
Stores user identity, roles, and administrative data. 3.1.2 Projects
The highest-level operational entity for scoping work and resources. 3.1.3 Project Members
A junction table for role-based project access. 3.1.4 Jobs (Requisitions)
Defines open positions for recruitment. 3.1.5 Candidates
Stores information about individuals applying for jobs. 3.1.6 Tasks
Represents discrete units of work within a project. The structure of this data model provides the foundation for the security model that governs how users can access and interact with this data. 4.0 Security, Access Control & Multi-Tenancy
Given the multi-tenant nature of the TalentOps platform, a robust and granular security model is of critical importance. The platform employs a dual-layer strategy to enforce strict data isolation and role-based permissions, ensuring that users can only access the data and perform the actions appropriate to their designated roles. 4.1 Dual-Role Authorization System
This dual-role model was chosen over a simpler, single-role system to provide the distinct layers of access required by a hierarchical enterprise SaaS product. It provides both high-level oversight for executives and granular operational control for project leads and members. Authorization is managed through a two-tiered role system, where a user's total set of permissions is an intersection of their broad global role and their specific, contextual project role(s).
designated roles. 4.1 Dual-Role Authorization System This dual-role model was chosen over a simpler, single-role system to provide the distinct layers of access required by a hierarchical enterprise SaaS product. It provides both high-level oversight for executives and granular operational control for project leads and members. Authorization is managed through a two-tiered role system, where a user's total set of permissions is an intersection of their broad global role and their specific, contextual project role(s). Global Role: This role is defined in the profiles.role field and governs high-level platform access and visibility. For example, a user with an "Executive" role can view analytics dashboards that aggregate data across all projects, whereas other roles cannot. Project Role: This role is defined in the project_members.role field and controls a user's specific action permissions within the context of an assigned project. For instance, a "Team Lead" may be permitted to upload documents to their project but is restricted from accessing or modifying documents in other projects. 4.2 Data Isolation Mechanisms
To enforce the permissions defined by the dual-role system, data isolation is implemented at two distinct levels of the technology stack. Application Level: The primary method for data scoping is programmatic filtering within the backend application logic. All data retrieval queries are constructed with WHERE clauses (e.g., WHERE project_id = ...) that restrict the result set to the user's currently active project context. Database Level (RLS): As a definitive security backstop, the system leverages Supabase's Row Level Security (RLS). This pushes security enforcement directly into the database engine itself. RLS policies ensure that even if an application-level filter were to fail or be bypassed, the database would still prevent unauthorized data access. The following SQL statement is an example of an RLS policy applied to the project_documents table.
the result set to the user's currently active project context. Database Level (RLS): As a definitive security backstop, the system leverages Supabase's Row Level Security (RLS). This pushes security enforcement directly into the database engine itself. RLS policies ensure that even if an application-level filter were to fail or be bypassed, the database would still prevent unauthorized data access. The following SQL statement is an example of an RLS policy applied to the project_documents table. This policy ensures that a user can only select (view) documents if they are a member of the project to which the document belongs. CREATE POLICY view_project_documents ON project_documents
FOR SELECT
USING (
  EXISTS (
    SELECT 1 FROM project_members
    WHERE project_members.project_id = project_documents.project_id
    AND project_members.user_id = auth.uid()
  )
);
With this secure data access model in place, the system can reliably support specialized subsystems for analytics and AI that consume this data. 5.0 Specialized Subsystems
The core data model is designed to support several specialized subsystems that deliver advanced functionality. This section details the architecture for the analytics and reporting engine and the AI-driven features powered by the vector data model. 5.1 Analytics and Reporting Engine
TalentOps utilizes a Transactional Analytics approach for its reporting capabilities. Instead of maintaining separate, pre-aggregated data tables for analytics, reports are generated in real-time by querying the operational data directly. This ensures that all dashboards and reports reflect the most current state of the system without data latency. Key reporting areas are sourced from the following operational tables:
Project Health: Metrics are generated by counting tasks per project and categorizing them by status (e.g., completed vs. pending). Manpower: Reports on team composition and allocation are derived from aggregations of profiles joined with project_members to provide a project-specific view of personnel.
querying the operational data directly. This ensures that all dashboards and reports reflect the most current state of the system without data latency. Key reporting areas are sourced from the following operational tables: Project Health: Metrics are generated by counting tasks per project and categorizing them by status (e.g., completed vs. pending). Manpower: Reports on team composition and allocation are derived from aggregations of profiles joined with project_members to provide a project-specific view of personnel. Financials: Financial reporting is sourced directly from the employee_finance table (a specialized table not detailed in the core entity list), filtered by employees with an active employment status. 5.2 AI & Vector Data Model (RAG)
The platform's AI subsystem is built on a Retrieval-Augmented Generation (RAG) architecture. Its primary purpose is to enable AI-assisted workflows, such as a context-aware chatbot that can answer questions based on project-specific documentation, enhancing user productivity and knowledge discovery. The data flow and components of the RAG system are as follows:
Storage: Source documents, such as PDFs and text files, are securely stored in Supabase Storage and linked to their respective projects. Embedding: When a document is uploaded, it is automatically chunked into smaller segments. Each segment is then processed by an embedding model and converted into a 1536-dimensional vector representation. Search & Retrieval: Semantic search queries are performed against a ChromaDB vector index. Crucially, every search operation is filtered by the user's project context. This filtering is a critical security measure that prevents data leakage by ensuring the AI can only retrieve and reason over documents belonging to the user's authorized projects. These subsystems lead into the final architectural component, which ensures the integrity and traceability of all data operations: the compliance and auditing system.
Search & Retrieval: Semantic search queries are performed against a ChromaDB vector index. Crucially, every search operation is filtered by the user's project context. This filtering is a critical security measure that prevents data leakage by ensuring the AI can only retrieve and reason over documents belonging to the user's authorized projects. These subsystems lead into the final architectural component, which ensures the integrity and traceability of all data operations: the compliance and auditing system. 6.0 Compliance and Auditing
The audit_log table functions as the system's immutable record of all data mutations (CREATE, UPDATE, DELETE). Its primary purpose is to provide complete traceability for every significant action performed within the platform. This is essential for meeting compliance requirements, debugging complex issues, and providing a transparent history of data modifications. The structure of the audit_log table is designed for clarity and comprehensiveness:
This robust auditing mechanism provides a comprehensive and transparent history of all significant activities within the TalentOps platform. 7.0 Appendices
This section provides a collection of technical artifacts and code examples that offer concrete illustrations of the architectural principles and data structures discussed in this document. 7.1 Appendix A: Sample Table Schema
The following SQL CREATE TABLE statement illustrates the schema for the project_documents table, including primary keys, foreign key constraints, and default values. CREATE TABLE IF NOT EXISTS project_documents (
    id UUID PRIMARY KEY DEFAULT uuid_generate_v4(),
    project_id UUID REFERENCES projects(id) ON DELETE CASCADE,
    title TEXT NOT NULL,
    content TEXT,
    doc_type TEXT NOT NULL DEFAULT 'other',
    file_url TEXT,
    created_by UUID REFERENCES auth.users(id),
    created_at TIMESTAMP WITH TIME ZONE DEFAULT NOW()
);
7.2 Appendix B: Sample Data Transformation Logic
This JavaScript code snippet demonstrates a common pattern used in the frontend service layer.
